Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And what are we gonna be learning
about today is matter specifically
with how do we look at matter
when it comes to chemistry?
Uh, we are gonna be going through
this video from an introductory
standpoint, just so you can get the
fundamentals of how we look at things.
So in this course, the big
thing that we like to understand
is we go from the ground up.
And assuming that matter is, exists
as particles, so the smallest type
of pieces you can possibly imagine.
So, things like atoms, or even, what
even makes up atoms are smaller.
So, when we look at particles,
what exactly are we talking about?
How small?
Well, here I have a photo, as you
can see, of someone spraying a mist.
And we're talking on a
really, really small scale.
So if you think of this mist, that's
all here, and you think of the finest
little droplets that are in here,
we're kind of going to zoom on that
and we're looking at particles.
That are about that size and even smaller.
So imagine that small, but another
million or so times smaller than that.
So as small as you can possibly go down to
the atomic scale, whenever we are looking
at these things, we want to think of all
these little specs and the way that we're
looking at these particles is that they're
all spaced out and that generally we just.
portray how to, let's look at how we
exactly we portray all these little
different particles moving forward.
When
we're looking at particles, the
whole idea is that they are made up
of atoms from your periodic table.
Now, particle, I'm using that as
a very generic term just to refer
to something that's really small.
So in a lot of times when it comes
to courses, We like to show these as
very, very tiny atoms, and they're
usually represented by little dots.
So, whenever we have those little dots,
this is a way for us to really be able
to imagine and see all the different
atoms that are within a gas, or maybe
a solid, or any type of material.
Now, when it comes to molecules, well,
usually you'll see these little dots
and they're all stuck together, they're
glued together, meaning they are bonded.
So we'll use this word chemical
bonding very often from now on out.
So you'll see the dots are connected.
So what happens if these things are
connected and they're close together?
How can we look at these pictures?
So first off is looking
at the phases of matter.
So matter comes in many different
forms, so there's solids,
liquids, gases, and also plasmas.
But we're going to be focusing on those
first three because they're what makes
the most things that you will come across.
So solids, usually you are going
to be exposed to these around you.
So these are typically in a very
organized pattern, meaning that you will
commonly see them as a repeating pattern.
And we like to say that these
are crystalline as a result.
So crystalline, as you can see,
like we have this pattern, right?
Then we have 1, 2, 3.
Repeating, so many of these solids that
we have all around us, whether even a lot
of things that you have in front of you
have a specific crystalline structure.
If you look at all different geodes and
rocks, you actually see that many of
them have all kinds of unique structures.
in them.
In fact, if you look at sodium chloride
or table salt that you have at home,
it actually exists in a cubic shape on
the atomic level if you were to zoom in
on it with a very powerful microscope.
Now, do all solids exist this way?
No, if you kind of think of
things that are like rubber or
they have an elastic character.
These things are generally called
amorphous because they are more
disorderly and they just kind of
flop on top of each other, but
they're still tightly bound together.
They have a very high density typically
because of how close these are together.
So solids have a very definite, uh, volume
and they have a definite shape behind it.
And that's the important thing.
It's a definite volume
and shape versus liquids.
Liquids do not have a definite shape.
But they do have a definite volume.
Meaning that the atoms are still very,
very close together and they more kind
of slide and slither past each other.
Solids are all nice and close and
hunkered together, very nice and packed
where liquids are more go with the flow.
They're more relaxed as a result.
So these can, um, they will take the
volume of whatever container they're in.
So you think of a liquid, if I have
a cup of water, right, it's going
to take the shape of that cup.
If I were to dump the water
onto the countertop, it's now
the shape of your counter.
Or if it falls onto the floor,
it's now the shape of the floor.
It just takes whatever
thing holds it together.
Um, but you can measure the volume, right?
You could take all that water, put it in
a grad cylinder, measure it, and be able
to see that it has a very exact volume.
Now when it comes to gases, gases,
they do not have a definite shape
or a definite volume, meaning
that you can compress them.
Now why is that exactly?
And that's because atoms are like,
or gas atoms are like little billiard
balls that are free moving and.
Um, they exist very, very far apart,
meaning that between them, there's
a ton of empty space between them.
They move extremely fast,
generally has to do with the
temperature that is behind them.
So if they have a lot of kinetic energy
within them, they will move very quickly.
And if they are, have a lower temperature,
they'll move very, very slowly.
So typically you can try to
describe these things as very
fast moving most of the time.
So I like to think of gas particles
kind of like bouncing all over the
place, like a five year old hyped up
on sugar at a birthday party being
that they are going so incredibly fast.
So we have those three phases.
How can we try to classify?
All these, all the
things around us, right?
You can look around, maybe your room or
wherever it is that you're watching this
video, and you can see many different
forms of matter around you, whether it's
your laptop, your phone, maybe your desk,
where maybe your chair, your clothing,
you, all these things are different.
So how can we classify matter?
Well, the way that we do it
in the scientific communities,
we do it by composition.
What is it made up of?
There's two ways we can classify this.
We can either classify them as a
pure substance, meaning that it's
only made up of one type of particle.
One type meaning one atom
or one specific compound.
It could be one or the other.
Mixtures are whenever we have
essentially more than one type.
So if you take, uh, let's say
if you had air, for example.
Air has oxygen, nitrogen,
many other gases.
That would be a mixture.
Now, if you had, um, let's say only,
if you take like your salt shaker and
there's only sodium chloride inside
of it, that would be a pure substance.
So it can exist in a
couple different ways.
Pure substances can be both
elements and compounds, so it can
be both, and then mixtures can be
separated into two different forms
as well, which are homogeneous.
and heterogeneous mixtures.
Let's take a look at both so that way
we can understand exactly what they mean
and how we can understand what they are.
So the first one, which was the
elements and the pure substances.
So, these are when you have just one type
of atom, meaning that it could be, if you
take your p roc table, it could be any one
of those different atoms that are there.
Now, all atoms, they don't always
necessarily exist by themselves,
like this little top picture here.
Sometimes they might be bound to
themselves in different arrangements.
However, they are still just one atom.
So, an example like this is
something like O2, oxygen gas, right?
You're breathing in O2 right now,
but it's still one element, but
they just happen to be connected.
So it's a little
different than a compound.
Um, now other ways that you can have these
different elements all connected together
is when you have things called allotropes.
We really don't discuss them a lot in this
class, but it's just kind of nice to know.
Um, so if you think of carbon, right?
So if you burn something and that soot
that's left behind, that's carbon.
Now, if you put that under a
lot of pressure, you could get
coal or you can get graphite.
Or if you put it under enough pressure
and time, you can get diamonds.
All of those are all carbon, right?
And we look at a diamond versus coal.
They look nothing alike, but it's
all based on pressure and time.
So these are all different
versions of a pure element.
Now, the most important pure elements
for you to remember without just having
your periodic table is realizing that
whenever an element bonds to itself,
and there's only two of those atoms
bound together, so like O2, H2, N2,
these are referred to as diatomics.
So diatomic gases, there's seven of
them, I refer to them as the diatomic
seven, uh, you need to memorize them
for any chemistry course, or even any
future higher level chem courses, even
some, uh, if you're in respiratory
therapy or any type of biology courses
as well, they come up quite often.
So these seven types of gases, in
order to remember them, There's
hydrogen, nitrogen gas, fluorine,
oxygen, iodine, chlorine, and bromine.
Now, trying to remember all seven of
these diatomic gases can be a little
tricky, so I came up, I have a mnemonic
that I love to use I found online.
And it's have no fear of ice cold beer.
So if you remember that, right, the first
letter of each of these words represents
one of these elements that are over here
and I color coded them to help match.
So if you remember, have no fear
of ice cold beer, you will never
forget your seven diatomics.
So H for have, so that'd be hydrogen
and N would be nitrogen and so on.
This will be very helpful for you.
You need to memorize
them for future courses.
Now, these are your elements.
Compounds are, just to talk about them,
right, it's whenever you have two or more
elements that are bound together, meaning
they exist in a very fixed proportion.
One example of this is water, right?
You drink water every single day,
hopefully, if you're taking care of
yourself, but it always exists as two
hydrogen atoms to every one oxygen atom.
It's in a ratio.
Now, this is a pure substance.
If you have a clean glass of water and it
went through a filter, you can drink it.
And it is only water.
Now, if you decide to, if you have
salt as well, so sodium chloride.
in that solution as well.
Well, now all of a sudden you have
more of a mixture as a result, right?
It could be soluble, it could
be homogeneous, heterogeneous,
you can classify that.
But sodium chloride, NaCl, notice
that when you have this crystal
pattern, it's this repeating lattice,
so crystalline structure, but this
is a pure solid of only Na and Cl.
at ions that are connected together.
So you have that specific portion.
Um, when you are looking at these
now, um, pounds, they can also do all
kinds of cool chemistry that you can
break them apart and they decompose
into completely different pieces.
So you can see that.
So that's what we're going
to look at right now.
Right?
So what we're seeing here is
someone's putting sugar in this
container and they're dumping
sulfuric acid onto the sugar.
And immediately you notice
the properties of this, these
materials are immediately changing.
The sugar, right, is normally
a white crystalline solid.
The sulfuric acid was this clear solution.
Now all of a sudden you can see
that the chemical properties
are immediately changing.
They're very reactive together, right?
So they right change to black.
Now if I unpause it, you're going
to start seeing that it's already,
they're starting to bubble.
If you look very, very closely right here
and notice how there's bubbles forming.
And if you mix it and give it a little
bit of an agitation, you can see
the sugars dissolving and more and
more bubbles are starting to form.
It's going to start turning
darker and darker and a lot of
heat is going to be released.
So meaning that the temperature is
going to be changing and therefore
you're going to see this, um, it's very
thermodynamic process is occurring.
So if I unpause it again and this
happening in real time as well,
you can see all of a sudden it,
the volume is changing of this.
material.
That's because you're
creating something new.
You're creating a new chemical.
So the compound can, pure
substance can dissolve and
turn into something brand new.
So what this pure compound or sugar is
decomposing into is you can see it's
turning into pure elemental carbon.
So this is all carbon that's coming
out of this, so it's like a big carbon
snake that's coming off, and you can
see all of this gas that's, that's,
uh, completely evaporating off, um,
because of how hot this thing can be.
This is chemistry in action.
It's really one of my favorites,
but this thing's a big mess, so I
don't know if we do it in the lab.
The next part of our series
is looking at mixtures.
So there, there's homogeneous,
which means homo meaning same,
and then heterogeneous mixtures.
So what this is all about is that when you
have multiple pure compounds and they're
all mixed together This makes a mixture.
So homogeneous is when you can't
physically separate them So or so you
can't tell just by looking at it that
there is a difference between them.
They are uniform.
So an example of this would be something
like, um, if you have, uh, like air
or many other different types of
mixtures, like all these solutions of
nickel that I have up here, notice how
they're blue, they're purple, they're,
um, like a yellowy green, a teal.
So, all these are mixtures of
nickel with water, and they all
have completely different colors.
You can see that it's all completely
uniform, and even if you zoom in on it
on the atomic level, so just going off
my little particle drawings, notice
how all the areas are very uniform.
There's no rough patches anywhere.
It looks, you want to, if you took one
section from another, you wouldn't be
able to tell the difference, right?
So they're all the same.
So homogeneous is like, think of air.
It is one solid or one complete mixture.
You can't pick out like the
oxygen atoms from the nitrogen.
If you tried picking out air
in front of you, people are
going to think you're crazy.
Um, another homogeneous mixture would
be like milk, for example, right?
There's proteins in there, some
fat, um, also water, but you
can't see the different layers
unless it goes bad, right?
But if it's normal milk, it
looks just like normal, right?
But it's a mixture.
Um, now with heterogeneous, this
means that it's not uniform.
So you can actually see that
there are different, completely
different pieces of it.
So an easy example, think of
a hot fudge sundae, right?
You can, you have the fudge, the
caramel nuts, Jim sprinkles, all
these different things on top of it.
But if you wanted to, you could
pick out all the different parts.
You could separate them all out.
So by like maybe melting the ice cream,
like maybe filtering out different pieces,
you can take all these little parts out.
You're in the lab, you're going to
see different heterogeneous mixtures.
After a chemical reaction might occur, you
might see a solid form in the glassware.
And there's also the liquid water
layer, but notice how they're
separated from each other.
So this is a mixture
that is heterogeneous.
Another example is, think back to the
density videos I've shown before with
all the different layers there are.
Those are heterogeneous
because you can easily see the
different layers that exist.
So, that is one of the big things
when we're trying to separate these.
Look at all the little
pieces that we have.
Okay, so going forward, to distinguish
between all these different, all
the different property, all the
different pieces of matter and all
their properties, is that we have
physical and chemical properties.
So, these have been mentioned in
previous videos, um, but just to
quickly go over them, a physical
property, uh, does not require the
substance to change its identity.
So one easy example is that I always
like to use is let's say if we had like
something like let's say a napkin for
example, and if I were to take that
napkin and I were to rip it in half,
right, so let's tear it into pieces.
Is it still technically a napkin?
And one thing you can
say is, it is, right?
It's still a napkin
even if it's in shreds.
I could rip it apart again, and
again, and again, and I could have
all these little pieces of the napkin,
but they, it is still a napkin.
Um, another way to look at physical
change is, let's say if you have.
You get a glass, glass of water
and you have ice in it, over time,
the ice will melt into water, but
the ice was always water all along.
And heck, if you left your cup of
ice on the, um, on the count or
your cup of water on the counter for
let's say a week, all of a sudden
all the water will have evaporated
into water gas over time as well.
It's still water.
Chemical properties is whenever
there's something that is completely
changed and it's generally
due to the chemical reaction.
because you are actually having,
um, the composition is changing.
Uh, one of the ways that you could see
that was when you had, when we had the
sugar with sulfuric acid, it went through
a chemical change because its property was
that it could react with sulfuric acid.
All substances, all substances display
physical and chemical properties.
And the way that they display these is
through physical and chemical changes.
So we're always interested
in how things are changing.
So what kind of changes could
exactly could we have looking
forward is if you think of how
something new can be created, right?
You want to see that there's, um, uh,
you want to take those observations
and measurements that we're going to
be doing in the lab and record them.
So if I were to look at, let's say
the different of Flames that are
up here in the top right corner.
What do you observe?
Well, it's hot You know, you see
colors that light is being emitted
You can see that, you know If you
have their marshmallows a little
fire, you can see the color of them
is changing in front of you, right?
You can smell it.
There is changes if I look at this cup
here, right you see bubbles forming
meaning gases If you touch the side
of the container, maybe you'll see
heat is coming off of it, right?
There are evidence or observations of
new changes versus, let's say a physical
change is just when you take something
in, let's say you take a glass, right?
And you have that glass in your hand,
you smash it into a thousand pieces.
It's now just a thousand pieces of glass.
It's still the same thing.
Um, phase changes, which we'll talk
about in future videos as well, going
from melting, freezing, boiling,
evaporating, all of these are
just, are still the same substance.
They're not going through
a chemical reaction.
They're just changing.
So that's going to be what we're going
to be seeing up in the upcoming weeks.
Thank you so much for listening.
This is the idea of the basics
of matter, and I hope that you
enjoyed it a little bit and we
will be seeing more in the future.
Thank you so much for listening
and I'll see you all later.